所以让我们想想这个例子的关键教训。
So let's think about the key lessons of this example.
记住，这是我们一直在看的代码。
Remember, here's the code that we've been looking at.
那么它是安全的吗？
So is it safe from bugs?
好吧，很容易责怪sum的实现者
Well, it's easy to blame the implementer of sum
绝对值超过其规范允许的范围。
of absolute values for going beyond what its spec allowed.
因为它确实超出了规范允许的范围，
Because it did go beyond what its spec allowed,
它的规范没有提到任何关于改变列表的内容。
its spec didn't say anything about mutating the list.
我们说这是一个要求。
And we said that was a requirement.
如果你想改变其中一个参数
If you were going to mutate one of the parameters
那是传给你的，必须是
that was passed into you, had to be
你的规格允许这么做。
allowed to do so by your spec.
但实际上，传递不可变对象是一个潜在的错误。
But really, passing immutable objects around is a latent bug.
只是在等程序员
It's just waiting for some programmer
不经意地改变列表，经常
to inadvertently mutate that list, often
具有很好的意图，比如能够重用其他代码
with very good intentions like being able to reuse other code
或者获得更快的性能，但会导致
or getting faster performance but resulting in a bug that
可能很难找到。
may be very hard to track down.
另一个问题是容易理解吗？
Is it easy to understand is another question?
好吧，当你读main的时候，你会
Well, when reading main, what would you
假设绝对值和和？
assume about sum and sum of absolute values?
读者是否能清楚地看到这份清单
Is it clearly visible to a reader that this list is going
被其中一个改变？
to get changed by one of them?
只是在你读代码的时候不明显
Just not obvious in when you're reading code
突变可能发生的地方。
where mutations can happen.
下面是第二个例子。
Here's a second example.
所以我们看到了其中一个危险
So we looked at one of the dangers
将可变对象传递到函数中。
of passing a mutable object into a function.
让我们看看出现的问题
Let's look at a problem that arises
当从函数返回可变值时。
when you're returning a mutable value from a function.
所以让我们想想约会。
So let's think about date.
Date是一个内置Java类。
Date is a built in Java class.
它碰巧是一种可变类型。
And it happens to be a mutable type.
它里面有方法--让我们向下滚动一点--
It's got methods in it-- let's Scroll down here a little bit--
你可以设定时间，分钟，日期和时间
that allow you to set the hours and minutes and day and time
日期所代表的。
that the date represents.
假设我们读到一个方法
So suppose we read a method that's
应该决定春天的第一天。
supposed to determine the first day of Spring.
所以说明书上说，我们要在春天的第一天回来
So its spec says, we're going to return the first day of Spring
今年。
this year.
不需要争论。
Takes no arguments.
它只返回其中一个日期对象
And it simply returns one of these date objects, which
记住是可变的。
remember is mutable.
我们会掩盖它的内部运作。
And we'll gloss over how it actually works inside.
所以现在，我们用土拨鼠日来考虑
So for now, we'll think about it using the Groundhog Day
算法，包括询问某种啮齿动物
algorithm, which involves asking some kind of rodent when
春天就要开始了。
the start of Spring will be.
现在，客户端开始使用这种方法，例如，
Now, clients start using this method, for example,
计划他们春季派对的盛大开始。
to plan their big start of Spring parties.
所以在密码的其他地方，有
So somewhere else in the code, there's
一种叫做政党计划的方法
a method called party planning that
会打电话给春天的开始，然后安排这个派对的日期
is going to call start of Spring and get this party date
反对然后做些事情
object back and then do some things
或者发邀请函，不管我们需要做什么
and maybe send invitations, whatever we need to do
能够策划那个聚会。
to be able to plan that party.
所以所有这些代码都有效，人们都很高兴。
So all this code works and people are happy.
但现在独立了，两件事发生了，两个变化
But now independently, two things happen, two changes
发生在这个密码上。
happen to this code.
这是我们要开始讨论的地方
Here's where we're going to start to talk
为改变做好准备。
about getting ready for change.
首先是春天开始的实施者
First the implementer of start of Spring
意识到土拨鼠开始了
realizes the groundhog is starting
因为经常被问到而生气
to get annoyed from being constantly asked
春天什么时候开始。
when Spring will start.
换句话说，这是一个昂贵的算法。
This is an expensive algorithm, in other words.
所以代码被重写了，春天开始的代码
So the code is rewritten, the code of start of Spring
被改写成最多问一次土拨鼠，
is rewritten to ask the groundhog at most once,
然后把土拨鼠的答案存起来以备将来的电话。
and then cache the groundhog's answer for future calls.
所以我们要创建一个私有静态变量，static
So we're going to create a private static variable, static
这意味着它只有一个可能的价值。
meaning it has only one possible value.
一开始，它将是空的。
And initially, that's going to be null.
但当春天第一次来临的时候，
But as soon as start of Spring is called for the first time,
它将看到它的缓存为空。
it's going to see that its cache is null.
它将运行这个算法
And it's going to run that algorithm
找出土拨鼠的答案
to figure out what the groundhog's answer is
把它放在土拨鼠答案里。
and store it in groundhog answer.
然后永远地，土拨鼠的答案大概不会
And then forever on, groundhog answer will presumably not
不再是空的。
be null anymore.
每次调用它时
Every time this is called, it will simply
让土拨鼠直接回答这个变量
get the groundhog to answer directly from that variable
别再打扰土拨鼠了。
and stop bothering the groundhog.
所以这是一种非常常见的优化
So this is a very common kind of optimization
当你有一个缓慢的算法是你缓存的结果。
when you have a slow algorithm is that you cache the result.
所以这是发生的第一个变化。
So that's the first change that happens.
但同时，另一个变化
But simultaneously, another change
是《春天开始》的客户之一吗
is that one of the clients of start of Spring
决定春天的第一天
decides that the actual first day of Spring
对派对来说太冷了，所以他们
is too cold for the party, so they're
一个月后就要开派对了。
going to make the party a month later instead.
所以他们把春天的开始作为派对的开始
So they get the start of Spring into their party date
然后他们用
and then they advance it by one month using
其中一种突变方法。
one of these mutation methods.
顺便说一下，这段代码有一个潜在的bug
By the way, this code has a latent bug
以增加一个月的方式。
in the way it adds a month.
你可能想知道为什么。
And you might want to think about why that is.
那么，当这两个决定相互影响时，会发生什么呢？
So now what happens when these two decisions interact?
特别要考虑谁是第一个
Think in particular about who is first
去发现这个虫子。
going to discover this bug.
是春天的开始谁发现的？
Is it going to be start of Spring who discovers it?
会是派对策划吗？
Is it going to be party planning?
或者是完全无辜的第三部分
Or is it going to be some completely innocent third piece
也碰巧调用了Spring开始的代码
of code that also happens to call start of Spring
在同一个节目里？
in the same program?